<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xml" href="rfc2629.xslt"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<rfc ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-abarth-origin-07pre" category="std">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="The Web Origin Concept">
      The Web Origin Concept
    </title>
    <author initials="A." surname="Barth" fullname="Adam Barth">
      <organization>
        Google, Inc.
      </organization>
      <address>
        <email>ietf@adambarth.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.adambarth.com/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date month="October" year="2010"/>
    <workgroup>websec</workgroup>
    <abstract>
      <t>This document defines the concept of an "origin", which represents a
      web pincipal.  Typically, user agents isolate content retrieved from
      different origins to prevent a malicious web site operator for
      interfering with the operation of benign web sites.  In particular, this
      document defines how to compute an origin from a URI, how to serialize an
      origin to a string, and an HTTP header, named "Origin", for indicating
      which origin caused the user agent to issue a particular request.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">
      <t>TODO: Introduce the document.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="conventions" title="Conventions">
      <section anchor="conformance-criteria" title="Conformance Criteria">
        <t>The keywords "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHOULD", "SHOULD
        NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be
        interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119"/>.</t>

        <t>Requirements phrased in the imperative as part of algorithms (such
        as "strip any leading space characters" or "return false and abort
        these steps") are to be interpreted with the meaning of the key word
        ("MUST", "SHOULD", "MAY", etc) used in introducing the algorithm.</t>

        <t>Conformance requirements phrased as algorithms or specific steps can
        be implemented in any manner, so long as the end result is equivalent.
        In particular, the algorithms defined in this specification are
        intended to be easy to understand and are not intended to be
        performant.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="syntax-notation" title="Syntax Notation">
        <t>This specification uses the Augmented Backus-Naur Form (ABNF)
        notation of <xref target="RFC5234"/>.</t>

        <t>The following core rules are included by reference, as defined in
        <xref target="RFC5234"/>, Appendix B.1: ALPHA (letters), CR (carriage
        return), CRLF (CR LF), CTL (controls), DIGIT (decimal 0-9), DQUOTE
        (double quote), HEXDIG (hexadecimal 0-9/A-F/a-f), LF (line feed), OCTET
        (any 8-bit sequence of data), SP (space), HTAB (horizontal tab), CHAR
        (any US-ASCII character), VCHAR (any visible US-ASCII character), and
        WSP (whitespace).</t>

        <t>The OWS (optional whitespace) rule is used where zero or more
        linear whitespace characters MAY appear:
        <figure>
          <artwork type="abnf">
OWS            = *( [ obs-fold ] WSP )
                 ; "optional" whitespace
obs-fold       = CRLF
          </artwork>
        </figure>
        OWS SHOULD either not be produced or be produced as a single SP
        character.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="terminology" title="Terminology">
        <t>The terms user agent, client, server, proxy, and origin server have
        the same meaning as in the HTTP/1.1 specification (<xref
        target="RFC2616" />, Section 1.3).</t>

        <t>A globally unique identifier is a value which is different from all
        other previously existing values.  For example, a sufficiently long
        random string is likely to be a globally unique indentifier.</t>

        <t>A idna-canonicalization host name is the string generated by the
        following algorithm:
        <list style="numbers">
          <t>Convert the host name to a sequence of NR-LDH labels (see
          Section 2.3.2.2 of <xref target="RFC5890" />) and/or A-labels
          according to the appropriate IDNA specification <xref
          target="RFC5891" /> or <xref target="RFC3490" /> (see <xref
          target="idna-migration" /> of this specification)</t>

          <t>Convert the labels to lower case.</t>

          <t>Concatenate the labels, separating each label from the next
          with a %x2E (".") character.</t>
        </list>
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="origin" title="Origin">
      <t>An origin represents a web principal.  Typically, user agents determine
      the origin of a piece of content from the URI from which they retrieved
      the URI.  In this section, we define how to compute an origin from a
      URI.</t>

      <t>The origin of a URI is the value computed by the following algorithm:
      <list style="numbers">
        <t>If the URI does not use a server-based naming authority, or if the URI
        is not an absolute URI, then return a globally unqiue identifier.</t>

        <t>Let scheme be the scheme component of the URI, converted to
        lowercase.</t>

        <t>If the implementation doesn't support the protocol given by
        scheme, then return a globally unique identifier.</t>

        <t>If scheme is "file", the implementation MAY return an
        implementation-defined value.
        <list>
          <t>NOTE: Historically, user agents have granted the file a tremendous
          amout of authority.  However, granting all local files such wide
          privileges can lead to privilege escalation attacks.  Some user
          agents have had success grant local files directory-based privileges,
          but this approach has not been widely adopted.  Other user agent use
          a globally unique identifier for file URLs, which is the most secure
          option.</t>
        </list>
        </t>

        <t>Let host be the idna-canonicalization of the host component of
        the URI.</t>

        <t>If there is no port component of the URI:
        <list>
          <t>Let port be the default port for the protocol given by
          scheme.</t>
        </list>
        Otherwise:
        <list>
          <t>Let port be the port component of the URI.</t>
        </list>
        </t>

        <t>Return the tuple (scheme, host, port).</t>
      </list>
      </t>

      <t>Implementations MAY define other types of origins in addition to the
      scheme/host/port tuple type defined above.  For example, an
      implementation might define an origin based on a public key or an
      implementation might append addition "sandbox" bits to a scheme/host/port
      tuple.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="same-origin" title="Comparing Origins">
      <t>To origins are "the same" if, and only if, they are identicial.  In
      particular:
      <list style="symbols">
        <t>If the two origins are scheme/host/port tuples, the two origins are
        the same if, and only if, they have identical schemes, hosts, and
        ports.</t>

        <t>An origin that is globally unique identifier cannot be the same as
        an origin that is a scheme/host/port tuple.</t>

        <t>Two origins that are globally unique identifiers cannot be the same
        if they were created at different times, even if they were created for
        the same URI.</t>
      </list>
      </t>

      <t>Two URIs are the same-origin if their origins are the same.
      <list>
        <t>NOTE: It is possible for a URIs to not be same-origin with itself.
        For example, a data URIs is not same-origin with itself because data
        URIs do not use a server-based naming authority and hence have globally
        unique identifiers as origins.</t>
      </list>
      </t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="serialization" title="Serializing Origins">
      <t>This section defines how to serialize an origin to a unicode string
      and to an ASCII string.</t>

      <section anchor="unicode-serialization"
               title="Unicode Serialization of an Origin">
        <t>The unicode-serialization of an origin is the value returned by the
        following algorithm:
        <list style="numbers">
          <t>If the origin is not a scheme/host/port tuple, then return the
          string
          <list style="empty">
            <t>null</t>
          </list>
          (i.e., the code point sequence U+006E, U+0075, U+006C, U+006C) and
          abort these steps.</t>

          <t>Otherwise, let result be the scheme part of the origin
          tuple.</t>

          <t>Append the string "://" to result.</t>

          <t>Append the [TODO: IDNA ToUnicode] algorithm to each component of
          the host part of the origin tuple, and append the results of each
          component, in the same order, separated by U+002E FULL STOP code
          points (".") to result.</t>

          <t>If the port part of the origin tuple is different than the default
          port for the protocol given by the scheme part of the origin tuple:
          <list>
            <t>Append a U+003A COLON code points (":") and the given port, in
            base ten, to result.</t>
          </list>
          </t>

          <t>Return result.</t>
        </list>
        </t>

        <t>[TODO: Check that we handle IPv6 literals correctly.]</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="ascii-serialization"
               title="ASCII Serialization of an Origin">
        <t>The ascii-serialization of an origin is the value returned by the
        following algorithm:
        <list style="numbers">
          <t>If the origin is not a scheme/host/port tuple, then return the
          string
          <list style="empty">
            <t>null</t>
          </list>
          (i.e., the code point sequence U+006E, U+0075, U+006C, U+006C) and
          abort these steps.</t>

          <t>Otherwise, let result be the scheme part of the origin tuple.</t>

          <t>Append the string "://" to result.</t>

          <t>Append the host port of the origin tuple to result.</t>

          <t>If the port part of the origin tuple is different than the default
          port for the protocol given by the scheme part of the origin tuple:
          <list>
            <t>Append a U+003A COLON code points (":") and the given port, in
            base ten, to result.</t>
          </list>
          </t>

          <t>Return result.</t>
        </list>
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="origin-header" title="The HTTP Origin header">
      <t>This section defines the HTTP Origin header.</t>

      <section anchor="origin-header-syntax" title="Syntax">
        <t>The Origin header has the following syntax:
        <figure>
          <artwork type="abnf">
            <![CDATA[
origin              = "Origin:" OWS origin-list-or-null OWS
origin-list-or-null = "null" / origin-list
origin-list         = serialized-origin *( SP serialized-origin )
serialized-origin   = scheme "://" host [ ":" port ]
                    ; <scheme>, <host>, <port> productions from RFC3986
            ]]>
          </artwork>
        </figure>
        </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="origin-header-semantics" title="Semantics">
        <t>When included in an HTTP request, the Origin header indicates the
        origin(s) that caused the user agent to generate the request.</t>

        <t>For example, consider a user agent that executes scripts on behalf
        of origins.  If one of those scripts causes the user agent to issue an
        HTTP request, the user agent might wish to inform the server that the
        request was issued by the script using the Origin header.</t>

        <t>In some cases, a number of origins contribute to causing the user
        agents to issue an HTTP request.  In those cases, user agent can list
        all the origins in the Origin header.  For example, if the HTTP request
        was initially generated by one origin, but then later redirected by
        another origin, the user agent might wish to inform the server that two
        origins were invovled in causing the user agent to generate the
        request.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="origin-header-ua-requirements"
               title="User Agent Requirements">
        <t>The user agent MAY include an Origin header in any HTTP request.</t>

        <t>The user agent MUST NOT include more than one Origin header field in
        any HTTP request.</t>

        <t>Whenever a user agent issues an HTTP request from a
        "privacy-sensitive" context, the user agent MUST send the value "null"
        in the Origin header.
        <list>
          <t>NOTE: This document does not define the notion of a
          privacy-sensitive context.  Applications that generate HTTP
          requests can define contexts as privacy-sensitive to impose
          restrictions on how user agents generate Origin headers.</t>
        </list>
        </t>

        <t>When generating an Origin header, the user agent MUST meet the
        following requirements:
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>Each of the serialized-origin productions in the grammar MUST be
          the ascii-serialization of an origin.</t>

          <t>No two consequitive serialized-origin productions in the grammar
          can be identical.  In particular, if the user agent would generate
          two consequitive serialized-origins, the user agent MUST NOT generate
          the second one.</t>
        </list>
        </t>

        <t>If the user agent generated an HTTP request current-request because
        the user agent received 3xx Status Code response to another HTTP
        request previous-request for URI previous-uri:
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>The HTTP request current-request MUST include an Origin header.</t>

          <t>The value of the Origin header MUST be either:
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>The string "null" (i.e., the code point sequence U+006E, U+0075,
            U+006C, U+006C).</t>

            <t>The value of the Origin header in the previous-request.  The
            user agent MUST NOT choose this option if the ascii-serialization
            of previous-uri is not identical to the last serialized-origin in
            the Origin header of the previous request.</t>

            <t>The value of the Origin header in previous header extended with
            a space and the ascii-serialziation of the origin of previous-uri.
            The user agent MUST NOT choose this option if the
            ascii-serialziation of the origin of previous-uri is "null".</t>
          </list>
          </t>
        </list>
        </t>
      </section>

      <t>Whenever a user agent issues an HTTP request that (1) is *not* the
      result of an HTTP redirect and (2) is *not* initiated from a
      "privacy-sensitive" context, the user agent SHOULD set the value of the
      Origin header to the ASCII serialization of the origin that
      initiated the HTTP request.</t>

      <t>Note: This behavior differs from that of the HTTP Referer header,
      which user agents often suppress when an origin with an "https" scheme
      issues a request for a URI with an "http" scheme.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="server-behavior" title="HTTP Server Behavior">
      <t>HTTP Servers MAY use the Origin header to "defend themselves
      against CSRF attacks."  Such servers are known as "participating
      servers" in this section.</t>

      <t>Let the /origin white list/ of a participating server be a set of
      strings selected by the operator of that server.</t>

      <t>The string "null" MUST NOT be a member of the /origin white list/
      for any participating server.
      <list style="empty">
        <t>Example: The origin white list for the example.com Web server
        could be the strings "http://example.com", "https://example.com",
        "http://www.example.com", and "https://www.example.com".</t>
      </list>
      </t>

      <t>A participating server MUST use the following algorithm when
      determining whether to modify state in response to an HTTP request:
      <list style="numbers">
        <t>If the request method is safe (as defined by RFC 2616,
        Section 9.1.1, e.g. either "GET" nor "HEAD"), return "MUST NOT
        modify state" and abort these steps.</t>

        <t>If the request does not contain a header named "Origin", return
        "MAY modify state" abort these steps.</t>

        <t>For each request header named "Origin", let the /initiating
        origin list/ be the list of origins represented in the header:
        <list style="numbers">
          <t>If there exists a origin in the /initiating origin list/ is not
          a member of the /origin white list/ for this server, return "MUST
          NOT modify state" and abort these steps.</t>
        </list>
        </t>

        <t>Return "MAY modify state".</t>
      </list>
      </t>

      <t>
      <list style="empty">
        <t>Example: A Web server could modify state in response to POST
        requests that lack an Origin header (because these requests are sent
        by non-supporting user agents) and could modify state in response to
        POST requests that have an Origin header of "http://example.com",
        "https://example.com", "http://www.example.com", or
        "https://www.example.com".</t>
      </list>
      </t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="privacy" title="Privacy Considerations">
      <t>This section is not normative.</t>

      <t>The Origin header improves on the Referer header by respecting the
      user's privacy: The Origin header includes only the information
      required to identify the principal that initiated the request
      (typically the scheme, host, and port of initiating origin).  In
      particular, the Origin header does not contain the path or query
      portions of the URI included in the Referer header that invade privacy
      without providing additional security.</t>

      <t>The Origin header also improves on the Referer header by not
      leaking intranet host names to external web sites when a user follows
      a hyperlink from an intranet host to an external site because
      hyperlinks generate privacy-sensitive requests.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>This section is not normative.</t>

      <t>Because a supporting user agent will always include the Origin
      header when making HTTP requests, HTTP servers can detect that a
      request was initiated by a supporting user agent by observing the
      presence of the header.  This design prevents a malicious web site from
      making a supporting user agent appear to be a non-supporting user agent.
      Unlike the Referer header, which is absent when suppressed by the user
      agent, the Origin header takes on the value "null" when suppressed by
      the user agent.</t>

      <t>In some legacy user agents, The Origin header can be spoofed for
      same-site XMLHttpRequests.  Sites that rely only on network
      connectivity for authentication should use a DNS rebinding defense,
      such as validating the HTTP Host header, in addition to CSRF
      protection.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="iana" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>TODO: The "Origin" header should be registered.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="todo" title="TODO">
      <t>Think about how this interacts with proxies.</t>

      <t>Think about how this interacts with caches.</t>

      <t>Think about how this interacts with IPv6.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="implementation-considerations"
             title="Implementation Considerations">
      <section anchor="idna-migration" title="IDNA dependency and migration">
        <t>IDNA2008 <xref target="RFC5890" /> supersedes IDNA2003 <xref
        target="RFC3490" /> but is not backwards-compatible. For this reason,
        there will be a transition period (possibly of a number of years).
        User agents SHOULD implement IDNA2008 <xref target="RFC5890" /> and
        MAY implement [Unicode Technical Standard #46
        &lt;http://unicode.org/reports/tr46/&gt;] in order to facilitate a
        smoother IDNA transition. If a user agent does not implement IDNA2008,
        the user agent MUST implement IDNA2003 <xref target="RFC3490" />.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <!-- ack Larry Masinter, Anne van Kesteren, Jonas, Lucas, dveditz, Sid
    Stamm, Collin Jackson, Ian Hickson -->
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <!-- http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.XXXX.xml -->
      <reference anchor="RFC2119">
        <front>
          <title abbrev="RFC Key Words">
            Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels
          </title>
          <author initials="S." surname="Bradner" fullname="Scott Bradner">
            <organization>Harvard University</organization>
            <address>
              <postal>
                <street>1350 Mass. Ave.</street>
                <street>Cambridge</street>
                <street>MA 02138</street>
              </postal>
              <phone>- +1 617 495 3864</phone>
              <email>sob@harvard.edu</email>
            </address>
          </author>
          <date year="1997" month="March"/>
          <area>General</area>
          <keyword>keyword</keyword>
          <abstract>
            <t>In many standards track documents several words are used to
            signify the requirements in the specification. These words are
            often capitalized. This document defines these words as they
            should be interpreted in IETF documents. Authors who follow these
            guidelines should incorporate this phrase near the beginning of
            their document:
            <list>
              <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
              NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
              "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described
              in RFC 2119.</t>
            </list>
            </t>
            <t>Note that the force of these words is modified by the
            requirement level of the document in which they are used.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="14"/>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2119"/>
        <format type="TXT" octets="4723"
          target="ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc2119.txt"/>
        <format type="HTML" octets="17491"
          target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/html/rfc2119.html"/>
        <format type="XML" octets="5777"
          target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/xml/rfc2119.xml"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="RFC2616">
        <front>
          <title>Hypertext Transfer Protocol -- HTTP/1.1</title>
          <author initials="R." surname="Fielding" fullname="R. Fielding">
            <organization>University of California, Irvine</organization>
            <address><email>fielding@ics.uci.edu</email></address>
          </author>
          <author initials="J." surname="Gettys" fullname="J. Gettys">
            <organization>W3C</organization>
            <address><email>jg@w3.org</email></address>
          </author>
          <author initials="J." surname="Mogul" fullname="J. Mogul">
            <organization>Compaq Computer Corporation</organization>
            <address><email>mogul@wrl.dec.com</email></address>
          </author>
          <author initials="H." surname="Frystyk" fullname="H. Frystyk">
            <organization>MIT Laboratory for Computer Science</organization>
            <address><email>frystyk@w3.org</email></address>
          </author>
          <author initials="L." surname="Masinter" fullname="L. Masinter">
            <organization>Xerox Corporation</organization>
            <address><email>masinter@parc.xerox.com</email></address>
          </author>
          <author initials="P." surname="Leach" fullname="P. Leach">
            <organization>Microsoft Corporation</organization>
            <address><email>paulle@microsoft.com</email></address>
          </author>
          <author initials="T." surname="Berners-Lee"
                  fullname="T. Berners-Lee">
            <organization>W3C</organization>
            <address><email>timbl@w3.org</email></address>
          </author>
          <date month="June" year="1999"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2616"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="RFC3490">
        <front>
          <title>Internationalizing Domain Names in Applications (IDNA)</title>
            <author initials="P." surname="Faltstrom" fullname="P. Faltstrom">
              <organization />
            </author>
            <author initials="P." surname="Hoffman" fullname="P. Hoffman">
              <organization />
            </author>
            <author initials="A." surname="Costello" fullname="A. Costello">
              <organization />
            </author>
            <date year="2003" month="March" />
            <abstract>
              <t>Until now, there has been no standard method for domain names
              to use characters outside the ASCII repertoire.  This document
              defines internationalized domain names (IDNs) and a mechanism
              called Internationalizing Domain Names in Applications (IDNA) for
              handling them in a standard fashion.  IDNs use characters drawn
              from a large repertoire (Unicode), but IDNA allows the non-ASCII
              characters to be represented using only the ASCII characters
              already allowed in so-called host names today.  This
              backward-compatible representation is required in existing
              protocols like DNS, so that IDNs can be introduced with no
              changes to the existing infrastructure.  IDNA is only meant for
              processing domain names, not free text. [STANDARDS TRACK]</t>
            </abstract>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="3490" />
        <format type="TXT" octets="51943" target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc3490.txt" />
        <annotation>

          See <xref target="idna-migration" /> for an explanation why the
          normative reference to an obsoleted specification is needed.
        </annotation>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="RFC5234">
        <front>
          <title abbrev="ABNF for Syntax Specifications">
            Augmented BNF for Syntax Specifications: ABNF
          </title>
          <author initials="D." surname="Crocker"
                  fullname="Dave Crocker" role="editor">
            <organization>Brandenburg InternetWorking</organization>
            <address>
              <email>dcrocker@bbiw.net</email>
            </address>
          </author>
          <author initials="P." surname="Overell" fullname="Paul Overell">
            <organization>THUS plc.</organization>
            <address>
              <email>paul.overell@thus.net</email>
            </address>
          </author>
          <date month="January" year="2008"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="STD" value="68"/>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5234"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="RFC5246">
        <front>
          <title>
            The Transport Layer Security (TLS) Protocol Version 1.2
          </title>
          <author initials="T." surname="Dierks" fullname="T. Dierks">
            <organization />
          </author>
          <author initials="E." surname="Rescorla" fullname="E. Rescorla">
            <organization />
          </author>
          <date year="2008" month="August" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5246" />
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="RFC5890">
        <front>
          <title>Internationalized Domain Names for Applications (IDNA):
          Definitions and Document Framework</title>
          <author initials="J." surname="Klensin" fullname="J. Klensin">
            <organization />
          </author>
          <date year="2010" month="August" />
          <abstract>
            <t>This document is one of a collection that, together, describe
            the protocol and usage context for a revision of Internationalized
            Domain Names for Applications (IDNA), superseding the earlier
            version. It describes the document collection and provides
            definitions and other material that are common to the set.
            [STANDARDS TRACK]</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5890" />
        <format type="TXT" octets="54245" target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc5890.txt" />
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="RFC5891">
        <front>
          <title>Internationalized Domain Names in Applications (IDNA):
          Protocol</title>
          <author initials="J." surname="Klensin" fullname="J. Klensin">
            <organization />
          </author>
          <date year="2010" month="August" />
          <abstract>
            <t>This document is the revised protocol definition for
            Internationalized Domain Names (IDNs). The rationale for changes,
            the relationship to the older specification, and important
            terminology are provided in other documents. This document
            specifies the protocol mechanism, called Internationalized Domain
            Names in Applications (IDNA), for registering and looking up IDNs
            in a way that does not require changes to the DNS itself. IDNA is
            only meant for processing domain names, not free text. [STANDARDS
            TRACK]</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5891" />
        <format type="TXT" octets="38105" target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc5891.txt" />
      </reference>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
